Hello everyone, today
we have one more class
in cardiovascular
physiology and I will be
teaching you about
hemodynamics and circulation.
For this lecture we have
five learning objectives
and all of them will be focused
on understanding blood flow.
So for the blood flow
be constant in or body,
some parameters will
play a significant role.
For example,
velocity,
pressure,
vascular resistance, and cross
-section area of
the blood vessel.
We will also discuss
about blood pressure
and its components,
mainly focusing cardiac
output and total
peripheral resistance.
We will not discuss very
detailed regulation of
blood pressure in this
lecture because we have one
specific lecture just to
discuss blood pressure.
Here in the learning
objective 3 we will
predict some factors
that can change cardiac
output, stroke volume,
and pulse pressure.
In the learning objective
4, we will discuss
some concepts very important
to determine cardiac
output when we have
laboratory results in our
hands or physical
findings. And the learning
objective four, I really
would like to highlight
here because this is
something very important.
We will be understanding
the relationship between
blood flow and resistance.
And for that we
need to understand the
Poisson law and also
Laplace law. So those two
laws are very important
to understand hemodynamics
and circulation.
So hemodynamics refers
to the principles that
governs blood flow in the
cardiovascular system.
So it refers to
the principles that
drive the blood flow
in the cardiovascular
system. And that
includes velocity,
pressure,
cross-sectional area,
resistance,
and capacitance or compliance.
So, hemodynamics, in
other words, we could
think about fluid movement
or fluid dynamics.
So, what is fluid?
fluid is a substance
that flow and don't have
a specific shape for
example we have here
water oil blood honey so
these are all examples
of fluid and we will
be discussing a lot
about blood pressure
sorry blood as a fluid.
So the physical characteristic
of the circulation
so here we have this
schematic figure showing the
heart that is the pump that
will be pumping blood for
the whole body and all the
arteries and veins, all
these blood vessels are a
network of pipes and the
fluid that is running in
these pipes are the blood.
So here we start to discuss
us some concepts that
over and over you will be
seeing during the lectures.
The first one is stroke volume.
Stroke volume is
the volume of blood
pumped out of the
heart in each beat.
And cardiac output is
the volume of blood
pumped by the heart
per minute. So the
formula, the equation
for cardiac output is
stroke volume multiplied
by heart rate.
And the average normal,
let's say, cardiac
output in one individual
is around five liters
per minute, five liters
of blood per minute.
So there is a very nice
summary in the first aid that
will mention about these
concepts that we are
discussing right now, stroke
volume and cardiac output.
So we can compare
this vasculature, this
network of pipes, to
an electrical circuit.
So here we have the battery,
and then we have the current,
and we have all these
wires. So the battery
in our system would
correspond to the heart.
The wires is our pipes
that are our blood
vessels and here
we have the current
passing and in our
system we have the blood.
So the blood is the
current, the heart
is the battery,
and what are the
wires? The wires are
the blood vessels.
So the heart, the left
heart and the right
heart, they operate in
series, similar to here,
which means that the venous
return to the left the
heart is equal the venous
return to the right heart so
cardiac output from the
heart is the same of
the venous return to the
heart so the amount of
blood that leave the
heart should be equal the
amount of the blood
that return to the heart
So the vasculature, that
is this network of pipes,
we have pipes from
different size and different
diameters, long, short,
big diameter, very
small diameter, and the
composition also change.
So this figure I took from
Constanzo, a very simple
one, but showing that
the blood from the heart
right they come here in the
aorta and then go to the
arteriolus and then
go to the capillaries
and delivery the oxygen
and the nutrients
to the majority of our
tissues and then this
blood um from the small
capillaries now the veins
they will reach all the vein
system and then the vena
cava and return to the right
side of the heart so here
I have list arteries very
small arteries capillaries
small veins and veins and
interesting here in the middle
of the spine now you have
the composition of these
arteries so as you learn in
the previous lectures about
endothelial cells, smooth
muscle cells, all the vessels
have endothelial vascular
smooth muscle cells and
the adventitia, the external
part of the blood vessels.
If you look here
the arteriolus,
if you look all the arteries,
all of them have endothelium.
So endothelium is present
in all blood vessels 100
percent but let's look
for the smooth muscles we
have a lot for example
here that could be aorta a
lot vascular smooth muscles
arteriolus but in the
capillaries we almost we
don't have smooth muscles
pretty much we have only
endothelium and in the
veins interesting we have
all the components of the
the layers of the vessel
but the amount is much
smaller compared to the
arteries so this is one
difference basic difference
between arteries and veins
and for illustrate that here
we have the ascending aorta
this is this oops sorry
this is this artery that
have a lot vascular
smooth muscle cells it's
a very elastic muscle
blood vessels and here we
have a saphenous vein
is a vein so they have
endothelium but the amount
of muscle is much less
so this is important to
know for us understand
that for keeping the
blood flow constant
when they are passing
by these different
blood vessels. So
what happens with the
velocity when the blood
vessel passes the aorta?
What happens with the
velocity when the blood
vessel passes in the
arterioles? It will change.
The velocity will
change because the
diameter of those vessels
are all different.
So as we are mentioned
more and more right now.
So here I have just
basic terminology in
circulation. So blood flow
is the volume of the blood
that pass a given point
in the circulation in a
given period of time.
So it's volume per time.
Velocity measures the
distance moving in a given
amount of time. It's the
distance of displacement
of blood per unit time,
distance per time.
And then compliance
or capacitance or
distensibility is the ability
of the vessel to distend
and increase volume
with increasing
transmural pressure. How
much a vessel can increase
the volume of blood,
how much it can hold.
So here we have this
schematic figure.
So the artery has
this capacity of
distend to accommodate
the blood. So
let's start with the
first principle, that
factor, that play a
role in constant blood
flow. Remember, what
we want in our body
is that the blood flow
continues constant.
So here we have a schematic
figure showing
some blood vessels,
some arteries, and
the diameters start
to change because I
have all this branch.
So what we know is that
the blood flow should
be constant, independent
if the artery have a
higher, like big diameter
or smaller diameter,
the blood flow
should be constant.
So here we have an area
of 12 and here of 6.
What is the formula for
the velocity? Velocity is
equal to the flow divided
by the cross-section area.
So here the cross-section
area is higher, it's 12,
compare with this point
that's 6, it's half.
so when we put in the
formula so 12 is constant
this is the the blood
flow rate this is constant
here and here in the point
x and the point y what
is change is the cross
-section area in the x point
I have 12 and in the y
-point I have 6. And look
the results. That show
us that in the point y,
the velocity is higher.
It's higher because
the cross-section
area is smaller.
So the narrower the
vessel, the faster
the velocity of flow.
Because the velocity of
blood flow is inversely
proportional to the
vascular cross-sectional
area, the changes in
the vessel diameter
alter the velocity
of blood flow through
a vessel. So just
looking at this figure,
we see here one vessel
with a small diameter and
another one with higher
diameter. So just looking
these vessels and
knowing that the flow
should be constant,
so here the flow
is constant for all
the three vessels.
When I have increase of
the area, the velocity will
drop, but if I have a
decrease in the area, the
velocity will increase and
is exactly what we have
here in in the bottle
of this figure. So the
velocity is higher here
because the area is smaller.
So vascular cross-section
area and blood flow. So
velocity is equal the
flow divided by the area.
And what is area? Area is pi
multiplied by the
radians squared.
So when we look here
at this figure, we
have, let's start from
the bottom. We have
aorta, arteries,
arteriolas, and then very
small capillaries,
and then the veins.
So what we are
taking consideration
here is the total
cross-section area.
If we compare here the
total cross-section area of
capillaries and the cross
-section area of aorta,
the cross-section area of the
capillaries, the
total, is higher.
So the velocity
here, represented
here in the blue,
will be lower.
In the aorta, the
velocity is higher because
the total cross-section
area is smaller.
So it's inversely proportional.
So the velocity will
increase when the cross
-section area decreases. So,
to understand better
this relationship between
cross-section area of
the artery, velocity,
and how that play a role
in making the blood flow
constant, let's try
this practical question.
A man has a cardiac output
of 5.5 liters per minute.
The diameter of
his thoracic aorta
is estimated to
be 20 millimeters,
and the total cross-section
area of his systemic
capillaries is estimated to
be 2,500 centimeters square.
What is the velocity of
blood flow in the aorta?
Relate to the velocity of
blood flow in the capillaries.
So we know based on the
cross-section area and that's
something that you need
to remember is the total.
Who has higher
cross-section area,
total cross-section area?
The systemic capillaries
or the aorta?
The systemic capillaries.
The cross-section
area is much higher.
So I know the
velocity will be lower
compared to the aorta.
So again, this is a
schematic figure. So if we
compare the total cross
-section area of the capillaries
and the total cross
-section area of the aorta,
aorta has a
smaller cross
-section areas, so the
velocity of the blood
flow here will be
higher compared to
the capillaries.
So let's apply the
formula. Velocity
is the flow divided
by the area.
In the capillaries,
the flow is 5.5, so
the question gave
this number for us.
Divide by the total
cross-section area of the
capillaries. They also
provide that for us, 2,500.
That will give us 2.2
centimeters per minute.
I know this velocity
should be lower compared to
the aorta. So let's now
calculate for the aorta.
The only thing we need
to pay attention in this
question is that for the
aorta, they give us the
diameter of the aorta. They
don't give us the total
cross-sectional area of
the aorta. So we need to
calculate first the total
cross-sectional area.
So what is area?
This is the formula, right? Pi
multiplied by the
radians squared.
Pi is 3.14 multiplied by...
So, if the diameter is 20, the
radius are half, right? 10.
10 millimeters is the
same of 1 centimeter,
so 3.14 centimeter
squared is the
total cross-section
area of the aort.
Now, if we put these values
in the formula again,
so cardiac output is
the same, 5.5 divided by
3.14. Again, look how
higher is the velocity in
the aorta compared to
the capillaries. So this
brings us again for
this concept that higher
is the cross-section area
of the blood vessels,
lower will be the velocity. So,
in summary, to keep
constant blood flow, we
need to take into
consideration the cross
-section area of the
vessels and the velocity.
So, we talk about velocity.
The next, we will talk about
pressure and resistance.
So, velocity, pressure,
and resistance, they
play a role and keep
the blood flow constant.
Blood flow.
So, blood flow,
pressure, and resistance.
So the formula that involves
all these parameters
is derived from the Ohm's
law. That's a fundamental
law of physics that
say that current is
equal the voltage difference
divided by the resistance.
In relating Ohm's law
to the fluid flow now,
and the fluid we are
talking is the blood, the
voltage difference is
the pressure difference.
So if you have
here a vessel, you
have a pressure P1
and pressure P2.
So delta pressure
is P1 minus P2,
and P1 is always
higher than P2.
let's say initial and
final pressure so this
pressure difference you
can find in depend of the
test book you are studying
or another material
you are studying can also
be called as a driving
pressure perfusion pressure
or pressure gradient
and then here we only
we don't have only the
pressure difference, but
we have the resistance.
I'm pointing here for you.
And the resistance
is the resistance
of the flow offered
by the blood vessel
and its interaction
with the flowing blood.
So, the blood flow, based
on the Ohm law, blood flow
here is delta pressure
difference divided by resistance
and here very very
important concept the major
mechanism for changing blood
flow in the cardiovascular
system is by changing the
resistance of blood vessels
particularly the very small
arteries the arteriolus so
blood flow pressure and
resist again so this is the
same figure from the previous
slide. So the pressure
difference is estimated as
the pressure difference of the
blood between two ends of
the blood vessel segment.
And the flow is always from the
higher pressure to
the lower pressure.
Vascular resistance
to the blood flow
happens as a result of
the friction between
the flowing blood
and the intravascular
endothelium along the
inside of the vessel.
So let's dig a little
bit more in this
relationship between
pressure and resistance
playing a role in
the blood flow.
So here we have the formula.
Flow is proportional to
the delta pressure divided
by the resistance. So
just look in this formula,
we have a sense that if
the resistance increases,
the flow will decrease.
If the pressure
increases, the
flow will increase.
So let's start here in final A.
So we have here
one vessel, initial
pressure 50, final
10. The difference 40.
Here we We have
initial pressure 90,
final 10, so the
delta pressure 80.
Which vessel has
the higher pressure?
This one,
double.
So that means the
flow will double.
The flow in this
vessel will increase
two times because the
pressure increases.
How about in the panel B?
So, we have here
initial pressure 90,
final 10. So, the
delta pressure is 80.
In the vessel B, we have
initial pressure 180,
final 100.
So, the delta
pressure is also 80.
So, the delta pressure in
this vessel and in this
vessel are the same, so
the flow will not change.
In fact, the flow in this
both vessels are the same.
So let's bring this concept
to real life example.
So we have here an image
of an exam that they were
evaluating the blood flow
in the coronary arteries,
so they inject the contrast
and they identified
that one of the coronary
artery was 95% block,
and here is after some
procedures they implant
some stent and the vessel
was fixed right we can
see that the diameter is
not straight anymore so
what the ohm's law say
based on the ohm's law that
the flow is equal delta
pressure divided by
resistance so what we see
here because there is this
blockage in this artery,
something that's going
to happen, the resistance
is increased here.
If the resistance is increased,
the flow will decrease.
So flow is direct, is
inversely proportional
to the resistance.
So every time the
resistance increases,
the flow will decrease
and vice versa vice
versa so this is a case
of ischemia when we have
a decrease in the blood
flow so if we have a
blockage here that will
increase the resistance
for the blood flow
so that will decrease
blood flow because the
resistance increase the
blood flow decrease that
causes ischemia and can
lead to heart infarct.
Let's do this
practical question.
A 55 years old woman has renal
blood flow of 500
mL per minute.
Her renal artery
pressure is 100
mmHg and renal venous
pressure is 10.
What is the vascular resistance
of the left kidney
in this woman?
So here I try to incorporate
a question that puts
together what we are learning
and the renal physiology,
because that will help you
to understand the blood
flow in the renal system,
vascular, the role of
vascular resistance in the
blood flow for the renal.
So flow is equal
pressure difference
divided by resistance.
The flow here is 500.
Delta pressure is
the higher pressure
minus the lower
pressure, 100 minus 10.
So the resistance
will be this one.
So here it's just showing
us how we could calculate
the resistance if the question
given to us the flow and
the numbers that we can
calculate the delta pressure.
What most likely
increases in a patient
with a discompensate
heart failure?
So heart failure,
you will have a
lecture specifically
on this topic.
The reason I'm bringing
this example because
this is something that
can make you consolidate
better all these
hemodynamic concepts. When
we are studying heart
failure, you will
understand even better
this hemodynamic concept.
So heart failure is when
the pump, the heart,
is not working properly.
There is a failure.
And the symptoms basically
are shortness of breath,
chest discomfort or pain,
and they have swallowing
legs. this is when the
disease is discompensated.
So for put together, even
I think you will still will
have the renal, but there
is the cardiorenal syndrome
and that's why I bring
the heart failure example.
So in heart failure
example, what's
happened with cardiac output?
Cardiac output
decrease if a cardiac output
decrease the amount of
blood reaching the tissues
in general will decrease so
we have a decrease in renal
artery perfusion so that
will cause a decrease in GFR
or not going details because
you have lectures on that,
but that will activate
the Renine Agiotensin system
and cause vasoconstriction
in order to compensate this
decompensate heart failure.
And here again when
you have this the pump
the heart is not working
well so you have a
In heart failure,
you have volume
overload, reduced
cardiac output,
decreased cardiac output.
So, a classical example of
pathological condition where
we see decrease in cardiac
output is heart failure.
That will cause a decrease
in renal perfusion,
also decrease in
bioreceptory stretch,
and that will result
in vasoconstriction.
But a receptor extract,
I'm just highlighting here
because we will discuss
a lot about that in my
following lectures about
blood pressure regulation.
All right, so until now, we
did velocity, we did pressure,
and I left for the last one,
resistance, and I consider
this a very key concept
that we discussed here
in this lecture and is
highly, highly asking boards.
So the relationship
between resistant blood
vessels and blood viscosity.
So, you see, now I'm
introducing a new factor
here, viscosity of the
blood. This is described
by the Poisson equation.
Like I said,
highly asking in the boards.
So blood flow, as I showed
in the beginning of the
lecture, is equal delta
pressure divided by resistance.
But what is resistance?
Resistance takes in
consideration the length of the
vessel, how long and how
short this blood vessel is,
the radius, the diameter,
and the viscosity.
So resistance is equal
8 times the length
multiplied by the
viscosity divided by pi
radiance fourth power.
If we combine this
formula with this
formula, that's what
we will end up having.
So just looking at this
formula, we can see
if the viscosity of
the blood increases,
the flow will decrease.
If the length of the
vessel increases,
the flow will decrease.
But if the pressure,
delta pressure
increases, the flow will
increase. And if the
radius increase, it's
directly proportional
to the flow, so we
will increase too.
So this is the
Poizoui equation.
So here we have the length of
the vessel, and the resistance,
the radius, And then
now I'm introducing
this new factor,
that's the viscosity.
A good example when you
are studying about the
Poiseuille equation is
remember about anemia.
So during the anemia, the
number of red cells decrease.
So the viscosity decrease.
the viscosity if the viscosity
decrease the flow will
increase so the blood flow
in anemia condition is
increased so here is a summary
I'm just putting here for
whoever is already interested
to get engaged with the
USMLE boards studies,
there is a nice table there
that summarizes about the
resistant pressure and flow.
Everything that I have
discussed with you until now.
Let's do a practical question.
A 65 years old man with
peptic ulcer disease
comes to the emergency
department due to nausea,
blood in the feces
feels faint his blood
pressure is 90 per 40 so
is a low blood pressure
pulse is 100 per minute
so high and respiration
are 28 per minute
physical examination
reveals a lethargic men
with cold extremities.
The patient receives
blood transfusion.
However, the transfusion
rate is very slow and the
patient remains hypotensive.
So even they are
giving to this patient
blood transfusion, the blood
pressure remains low.
Which of the following will
lead to the greatest
improvement in flow rate?
So for this is,
again I choose this
question because
make us training and
I would say consolidate
this concept
that we are looking
about resistance,
velocity, pressure,
and blood flow.
And to answer this question, we
need to use the
Poislay equation.
So, the question
is, the flow is low.
What can we do to
increase the flow?
I could, if I look
what is directly
proportional to the
flow, the length
of the vessel and
the viscosity we,
in this patient,
I think this would
be very difficult to
do. So we can change
the delta pressure
or the radius.
So the delta pressure, if
you increase, the problem
to increase pressure
when you are doing a
blood transfusion is that
you can break the cells,
the red cells, and you don't
want that. So what we are
going to do we can increase
the radius so here what
we are talking about is
the the the radius of the
catheter that you are inserting
the patients to do the
blood transfusion so if you
increase the radius for from
1 for 2 the flow will
increase 16 times so doubling
the diameter of the intravenous
catheter will increase
the flow 16 times so the
right answer here is a just
as a curiosity that would
be a case of hypovolemic
hemorrhagic shock another
question a 22 years old
medical student presents
with three months history of
fatigue and complain of
feeling sleep most of the time.
She's found to have
a middle systolic
murmurs and higher than
normal cardiac output.
The differential
diagnosis based on these
finds includes which
of the following.
What I want to pay
attention here is
this increasing
cardiac output so when
we have increasing
cardiac output so
the answer here is anemia
so what's happening
anemia in anemia remember
the viscosity increase
so the flow decrease
and then you have less
red cells carrying oxygen
so as a compensate mechanism,
you have increasing
heart rate and increasing
cardiac output.
And this increase of
heart rate and cardiac
output is what is giving
these middle systolic
murmurs. So the correct
answer here is D.
So when the viscosity drop,
the flow increase.
Let me just correct
myself because
I think I said the opposite.
So in anemia the viscosity
decrease so the flow
will increase and the flow
increase we have increase
of heart rate and increase
in cardiac output.
I think this is one of
the last concept that we
are seeing here in this
lecture, the Laplace law,
that is about the wall
tension in a blood vessel.
So why does the wall tension
increase with the radius?
So based in the
formula, wall tension is
equal transmural pressure
multiplied by the
radius divided by 2
times wall thickness.
So if the radius increase
the tension in the wall of
the vest will increase
a classical example to
understand that is an aneurysm
so here we have an abdominal
aortic aneurysm so this
is a normal this is
aneurysm so you can see the
radius increase here so the
tension in this wall is
higher compared to this one
so here there is some they
sounds the same but they
are not the same that's why
I'm including this yellow
box so very in the
beginning of this lecture I
told you about arterial
compliance or arterial
distensibility is the elastic
property of the artery how
much they can accommodate
blood so as we age we lose
this arterial compliancy
property and the vest become
more stiff so arterial
stiffness is something that
we observe with aging process
all of us in one point
of the life when we are
older we will have stiff
arteries remember we have
stiff muscle when you start
to age and then you also
have stiff arteries is
when you lose the elastic
property of the rod vessel.
Arterial thickness
I mention here
because we mention
in the Laplace law.
Arterial thickness is how
thick is the wall of the
vessel that has not...
you can have arterial
thickness but you don't
have arterial stiffness it's
not they are different
concepts so this is just
to take your attention
that that doesn't mean the
same arterial compliance
stiffness and thickness
so blood pressure so
here i will not go much
in details because we
will have a lecture
only about blood pressure,
but blood pressure
is calculated as a
systolic and diastolic.
And then the mean
arterial pressure, there
is this formula, is
equal to diastolic plus
one-third of the post
-subpressure. Post-subpressure
is something now
I'm introducing for
you, is a new concept.
What is post pressure?
Post pressure is systolic
pressure minus diastolic.
So here again, I'll go
very brief. So this is just
showing the pressure
profile in the vasculature.
So you can see the pressure
is very high in the
aorta, right? In the
large vessels. And as they
reach the small, the
capillaries and the venules,
veins, the pressure
is very low.
So the high pressure
is in the arteries.
So for the entire
systemic circulation,
pulse pressure is
systolic minus diastolic.
Blood pressure equation
is cardiac output
multiplied by total
peripheral resistance.
Total peripheral
resistance and systemic
muscular resistance
means the same.
And here we have a
mean arterial pressure
can also be
calculated by 2 times
diastolic plus
systolic divided by 3.
And cardiac output
is same of aorta
pressure minus the
vina cava pressure
divided by total
peripheral resistance.
So let's put some numbers to
understand pulse pressure.
So here we have an
example of systolic
and diastolic blood
pressure, 100 per 80.
So pulse pressure would
be 120 minus 80 equal 40.
I just put here the
mean arterial pressure
calculation for you to try
later. so use these formulas
the numbers that i'm
giving here and see if you
get the same number so
independent of this formula
or this formula you're
supposed to get the same
number for mean arterial
pressure so a normal
pulse pressure is 30 to
40. so what pulse pressure
tell us when we need know
about pulse pressure.
I will explain in the
following slides, but keep
in mind, we need to discuss
about pulse pressure.
So the total peripheral
resistance also, I will
discuss in more details
in the blood pressure
regulation, but just to put
in the context here, the
total peripheral resistance
so here is the formula
of resistance delta
pressure divided by the flow
so i'm just saying now
the total peripheral is
the delta pressure
divided by the flow that's
cardiac output because i'm
talking about the total
the systemic so the
final formula that will
have total peripheral
resistance is the mean
arterial pressure minus
the central venal pressure
divided by cardiac output.
So we have factors
that control total
peripheral resistance.
They can be
local factors or in
extrinsic control.
So it can be heat,
cold, that can
play a role in the
total resistance,
total peripheral resistance.
And we have this another
factor, sympathetic
activity and some
hormones that can play
a role in the total
peripheral resistance.
So here again, just
to show you the
formula of the total
peripheral resistance.
So we need the mean
arterial pressure,
central venal pressure
and cardiac output.
So the pulse pressure that
I discussed with you that
is systolic minus diastolic
is a parameter that can be
used to understand if
there is, for example, some
change in stroke volume or
arterial compliance, because
these factors will change
the pulse pressure. So here,
in the first figure, I
have aortic valve stenosis.
If I have stenosis
here, what do you think
is going to happen
with the stroke volume?
Will increase or decrease?
Will decrease.
If stroke volume decreases,
the pulse pressure will
decrease, will drop. So this
is one example where we
find lower pulse pressure.
Here in the middle is
another example where
we have low pulse
pressure. So this is an
artery that is undergoing
some calcification,
some inflammation, and this
artery has a low compliance.
So this artery is not, the
distensibility is compromised.
So when the arterial
compliance decrease,
what we have as a result is
a drop in pulse pressure.
So in atherosclerosis,
we have a decrease
in pulse of pressure because we
have a decrease in
arterial compliance.
And here is an example where we
have an increase
of pulse pressure.
So here is a hyperthyroidism.
In hyperthyroidism,
we have an increase
in blood pressure, and
that will lead to an
increase in pulse pressure.
Now, we can have a
change in pulse pressure
in a physiological
condition. You don't
need to be sick or
under some pathological
condition to have a
change in pulse pressure.
And a simple
example is when you
are standing or
when you lay down.
So, when you lay down,
your pulse pressure
will increase because
you have increased in
central venous pressure.
So, the pressure here,
so here is the vein system,
right? So, the
pressure here is lower
because it's
against the gravity.
So, from the bottom
is going back to
the heart. But when
we lay down, we
increase the central
venous pressure.
That will increase the end of
diastolic volume.
that's the pre-load.
Increasing pre-load we
have increasing stroke
volume so more volume here
and that will increase
pulse pressure so
just the fact that you
lay down you can increase
your pulse pressure.
But here also I'm
introducing another
factor that's central
venous pressure
we don't talk about
this at all before.
And we will discuss
in the next slide.
This is just what
is in the USMLE.
I suggest you start
reading. They put very nice
examples when we have
change in pulse pressure. So
let's say when you are
measuring the blood pressure
of the patient, immediately
you can have pulse pressure
values. You take the
systolic minus systolic.
This number, if it's low,
can mean something. We saw
pulse pressure below in
atherosclerotic process,
aortic stenosis, and if the
pulse pressure is higher,
one example that I gave
was hyperthyroidism.
So pulse pressure is a
very useful parameter.
So I mentioned central
venous pressure.
So how we can measure that?
Usually it's invasive,
you need to put a catheter
to get this parameter,
and this corresponds to
the blood pressure in
the thoracic vena cava,
near to the right atrium,
and the normal central
venous pressure is very low
0 to 7 millimeters of
mercury so here is the
pressure that we have so as
go close to the heart this
is the venous system
everything I'm showing here
is venous system the
pressure is higher here in
and then is going close to
the heart oops they go to
zero so let's do this practical
question a 27 years old
medical student is sitting
in silence instead reviewing
cardiovascular physiology
she takes her pulse and
counts her heart rate to
be 75 beats per minute
her friend preparing for
ICC measurements, sorry,
measure her blood pressure
and tells her she has
a systolic pressure of
110 and diastolic of 70.
She knows her average
stroke volume is
65 mLs per beat. Based on these
informations, what is
the cardiac output,
the mean arterial
pressure, and the pulse
pressure? So I will
leave for you to
calculate that. It's
very straightforward.
The question
already provides all
the values you
need to calculate.
So in this case, for
calculate cardiac
output, you have the
physical calculation.
But we can also
calculate cardiac output
using the fixed
principle. So the physical
calculation is very
straightforward.
Cardiac output equals stroke
volume multiplied
by heart rate.
So you can have this number.
But how about if they
don't provide, for example,
stroke volume? You don't
know the stroke volume.
So it will be difficult
for you to calculate
cardiac output. So another
day, another way to calculate
cardiac output is using
the fixed principle.
So this is the formula
of the fixed principle
is the oxygen
consumption divided by
oxygen arterial minus
the oxygen venous.
For calculate
cardiac output based
on that, you need lab results.
This is very highly
asked in the boards.
So understanding how
you obtain cardiac
output values based on
physical calculation
and fixed principles
is very important.
So let's do some
practical questions.
A 17-year-old man presents
with the following parameters.
Here is all the parameters.
They are asking, what is
the patient cardiac output?
So here we don't
have, we have a
stroke volume, we
have heart rate.
So we just multiply 50 by 40.
But let's say you don't
have the stroke volume.
And then you would need to use
the fixed principle
to calculate.
So see if you find
the same number
using the two
different methods.
So here, just summarize
that cardiac output
is heart rate multiplied
by stroke volume.
What can change heart rate
is hormones, nerves and
physical activity. Every time
we exercise, we will increase
heart rate and that will
increase cardiac output.
But how about patients
that have received
cardiac transplantation?
We know that the
innervation from the
heart is all modified.
So,
if you have a cardiac
transplanted patient and
you put them to exercise,
the cardiac output
will increase. But not
because there is an
increase in heart rate.
Remember, during the
surgery all the nervous
supplies will change.
They will increase
cardiac output
because of the stroke
volume. They will
have an increase in
the stroke volume.
And in anemia, we
have a decrease
in the discoset of the blood.
We have increasing heart rate.
And that will have an
increase in cardiac output.
So this is an example where
we have increasing cardiac
output because we have
increasing the heart rate. So
here's the summary,
cardiac output
is heart rate versus
stroke volume,
and here we have the figure
of the preload and afterload.
So preload correspond to
the end of this is the
diastolic and the
afterload is the resistance
against which the blood
is ejected from the heart.
So we have a decrease in
stroke volume when we have
a decrease in preload.
So if the amount of blood
returned to the heart decrease
that means the preload
decrease we will have a
decrease in stroke volume
if we have one
increase in afterload
resistance so less
blood leave the heart
and then you have a decrease
in stroke volume aortic
stenosis for example we
have increase in afterload,
and when we have a decrease
in cardiac contractility.
So, here's the summary
of what we have
discussed in this second
part of the lecture,
the relationship
between cardiac output,
stroke volume, and heart
rate, all the factors that
can change cardiac output,
if we have a change
in stroke volume, heart
rate, what is the factors
that change stroke volume
heart rate and here we
have the final question
that summarized my whole
lecture I will not answer
the question with you this
is a homework I would like
that you try to answer
this question see what
is the number you get and
if you have any question
or have difficulty to
answer discretion please
reach out to me this is
my email and that's all
for this lecture thank you